A Guide to the Randolph Family Papers, 1783-1909, 1791-1909
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Randolph Family Papers 1783-1909, 1791-1909
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6225
This collection consists of ca. 190 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Mary Walker Randolph, Chapel Hill, N.C., 1960 February 23.
Scope and Content
Chiefly family correspondence of Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Agnes (Dillon) Randolph and Margaret Smith (Randolph) Randolph. However, there are letters from Dabney Carr, Ellen Wayles (Randolph) Coolidge, Francis Wayles Eppes, Robert Garlick Kean Hill, James J. Monroe, Nicholas Philip Trist, Bernard Peyton, Wilson Cary Nicholas, Thomas Sully and William Henry Roane.
Includes letters, 1802 March 3, 1803 February 24, Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Thomas Jefferson and, various memoranda, designs and sketches, and calling cards.
In addition there are the following: land grant, 1798 February 5, to W.C. Nicholas for property in Amherst County, Virginia; survey, 1791 July 2, by Elliot Lacy of land in Goochland County, Virginia; letters and invoices, 1863-1864, to Major T. J. Randolph of the Confederate States of America Quartermaster Corp. for army supplies; letters, 1884-1888, from Paul Otto and F. Otto Schulze to Sarah Nicholas Randolph, secretary of the Lee Monument Association, re the statue of Robert E. Lee in Richmond, Virginia.
Contents List
- Thomas Jefferson Bill of Scantling delivered to Mr. Frazer,1783 June, AD. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Original in Thomas Jefferson Architectural Drawings, Box 1.
- Thomas Jefferson Design with Sketch for Desk, [1790], AD. 1 pp. N-436. (Box-folder 1:1A)
  Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.
- Survey of Land on the Rivanna River, 1791 July 2, ADS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Drawing of the land surveyed by Elliot Lacy.
- Jo[seph] Monroe to [Thomas Mann Randolph]?, 1794 September 29, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Introducing Thornton Gilmer, who will act as his representative in the cavalry under Randolph's command.
- Wilson Cary Nicholas' Land Patent, 1798 February 5, ADS, 1 p. Oversize Box W-5. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Thomas Jefferson Notes on Mileages, [1800], AD. 2 pp. (Box-folder 1:4A)
  Lists Monticello, Thornton Gap, Ruffner's, Cunningham's Mill, Rockfish Gap, Kennerley's, Madison's Cove, Jones's, Gilbert's, Narrow Passage, Rappidan, Robinson River, Brown's Culpeper Court House, Hedgeman River, Fauquier Court House, Germantown, [Pa.?], Widow Nevill's, West's Ordinary, Leesburg, Knowland's Ferry, Zane's, Winchester, Threetons, McCormack's, Harper's Ferry, Frederictown, [Md.?], Bentley's. Taverns listed, Leesburg: McEntire's, Indian King; Frederictown: Crush's, Sycamore Tree; Tawney Town: Mrs. Charlton's, Caleb's, Bacchus and Threetons; Petersburg: Kurtz's, The Swan; McAllister's Town: Rhenegher's; Yorktown: White's, Sign of the Lemon; Lancaster: Rickhart's, The Bear. Other towns: Alexandria, Colchester, Dumfries, Lansdowne, Elkrun Church, Piscotaway, Port Tobacco, Howe's Ferry, Port Royal, Bowling Green, Hanover Court House, Goodall's, Richmond.
- Thomas Jefferson Sketch for House and Dependency, [1800], AD. 1 pp. Fragment. Addressed on verso to T. J., Albemarle. See Nichols, N-465. (Box-folder 1:4B)
- Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Thomas Jefferson, 1802 March 3 [date received], ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. (Box-folder 1:4C)
  Latin improves. Goes in spring to Latin school with Beverly Randolph. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.
- Dabney Carr to Thomas Mann Randolph, 1802 May 2, ALS, 2 pp. with separate address leaf; docketed. (Box-folder 1:5)
  Requesting Randolph's assistance in ascertaining whether the claim of the bearer of the letter, John Gardner, that he has discovered a very valuable mineral on his land, has any veracity.
- Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Thomas Jefferson, 1803 February 24, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. (Box-folder 1:5A)
  No measles. Virginia speaks well. Ellen learns French. Cornelia sends love. Wants geography book. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.
- John Cox Receipt Thomas Jefferson, 1804 August 13, ADS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. (Box-folder 1:5B)
  For 5 ¾ yards lace muslin for Mrs. Madison. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.
- Drawing of Oak Leaves by F[rancis Wayles] Eppes, [1815?], ADS, 1 p.; silked. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Wilson C[ary] Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1816 March 22, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Desiring Randolph's return as a result of the illness of his wife, Jane [Hollins (Nicholas) Randolph], following the birth of their daughter, [Margaret Smith Randolph].
- Accounts of Thomas Jefferson Randolph, [1818 to 1838], ADs, 5 items; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Accounts for various household items, and one containing medical expenses for slaves.
- R. Peyton to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1818 April 27, ALS, 1 p. with address on verso; docketed; postmarked Richmond VA, April 27; Barrow. Concerning a shipping error. (Box-folder 1:9)
- [Martha Jefferson Randolph] to Margaret Randolph, 1826 April 27, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Concerning a student's dinner at her home, a time for Margaret to practice on the harpsichord, and desiring a visit.
- [Thomas Jefferson Randolph] to Martha Jefferson Randolph, 1826 December 18, AL, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso. Signature clipped. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Concerning his decision not to publish the memoir, but the whole works by subscription, and the possible sale of a bust to the Legislature of Louisiana. Randolph also mentions the reason for his visit to Washington was to see if any thing would be done by Congress for [their] relief more from a sense of duty than any hope of success, and that they must rely on their own resources for succor during their time of financial distress.
- M[ary] P[age] R[andolph] to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1827 March 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Informing her cousin about various family matters, her studies, and her upcoming attendance at a dancing school.
- Margaret Smith Randolph's Edgehill School Reports, [1828 to 1829], ADs, 13 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
  A majority of these grade reports are written and signed by her instructor, H. C. Stearns.
- M[ary] P[age] R[andolph] to Margaret Randolph, 1828 October 1[5], ALS, 2 pp. with attached address leaf; postmarked Lynchburg, VA, October 17. (Box-folder 1:14)
  Concerning her very dull prospect of a school, her sole remaining boarder, Ann Jeffress, and providing them with information about past students at her school.
- H[arriet] Randolph to [Margaret Smith] Randolph, 1828 November 6, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Thanking her for her letter, her intentions to quit the state [of Virginia] because of her school's lack of success and the closing of many schools in the area due to the outcry of hard times, and her optimism about conditions in Florida.
- Septimia Randolph to Margaret Smith Randolph, [ca. 1830 to 1835], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Lamenting the loss of her little jar, which was the last thing given [her] by her poor Mammy whom [she] shall never cease to think of without the deepest regret [she] had but little idea when last [she] saw her, that [they] shall never again meet in this world of trouble and care, it is selfish to wish to have her back for she is now happy, far better off than [she is]. [Septimia] wish[es] that [Margaret] would keep a look out for the little thing. [Septimia] got a letter from [her] Daddy in which he sent [them] some hair of hers. Septimia also inquires about a squirrel that Margaret has named after her.
- Septimia and Mary Jefferson Randolph to M[argaret] S[mith] Randolph, [ca. 1830 to 1835], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked City of Washington [June]?; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:17)
  Relating her possible return to Virginia from Washington, and her sister Ellen [Wayles Randolph Coolidge] and brother Lewis [Randolph]'s visit.
- B[enjamin] F[ranklin] Randolph to Margaret [Smith] Randolph, [ca. 1830 March 18], ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:18)
  Relating his fondness for and recollections of Edgehill, concerning his first patient, and laments a dearth of young available women near him. He goes on to relate an anecdote about a marriage lottery that he had heard from an old gentleman acquaintance of his, but laments being unable to find a manager for this plan who can be trusted with all the love secrets of the county.
- C[ornelia] J[efferson] R[andolph] and Septimia Randolph to Margaret Smith Randolph, [ca. 1830 to 1835] June 7, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked City of Washington, June 7; Barrow. Reproaching them for neither visiting nor writing them, and expecting Margaret soon. (Box-folder 1:19)
- Septimia Randolph to "Meg" [Margaret Smith Randolph], [ca. 1830 to 1835] August 8, ALS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 1:20)
  Concerning family matters.
- Septimia [Randolph] to Margaret Smith Randolph, [ca. 1830 to 1835] September 24, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked City of Washington, September 26; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:21)
  Concerning Brother L[ewis Randolph]'s reception in Washington, and relating that a member of congress would request her brother [Thomas] Jeff[erson Randolph]'s appearance with "a bust of grandpapa" [Thomas Jefferson]. Also mentions the subsiding of a cholera outbreak in Washington, although their brother Lewis [Randolph]'s "favorite physician" Dr. Thomas is possibly ill with it, and that she has refrained for going out for fear of it. She also describes "Little Jeffy's" illness, and asks whether Margaret can inquire whether or not Evelina Garret is yet living.
- "Molly" [Mary Buchanan] Randolph to Thomas J[efferson Randolph Jr.] and Wilson [Cary] N[icholas] Randolph, [ca. 1830 to 1839] September 25, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:22)
  Concerning recent rainfall and flooding, ruined tobacco and corn crops as well as damaged bridges and roads near Edgehill.
- Mrs. W. T. to "The Misses Randolph," [ca. 1830 to 1839], October 20, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:23)
  Requesting that the misses Randolph bring Septimia Randolph [Meikleham] to visit if she is with them. Desiring a waltzing party, and describes the waltzing skills of several of their acquaintances.
- S[eptima] A[nne] C[ary] R[andolph] to Miss Margaret [Smith] Randolph, [ca. 1830 to 1839], November 13, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked, City of Washington, November 18; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:24)
  Relating that she tires of the city life, and longs to return to her "own dear Mountains." She also relates her fondness for the young physician who has just treated her, and provides a description of her dress for the wedding of Miss Harriet Watson.
- [Unidentified] to Miss Margaret [Smith] Randolph, [ca. 1830 to 1839] Thursday morning, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:25)
  Deploring her propensity for going to parties, and claims that he does not have the time "to race about the country to every little kick up of a parade." Inquiring about the frequency of Cousin William's visits to Edgehill. Also requests that Margaret tell her mother that there are no peaches to be found, but that he will send her some of his preserved apples as soon as they are ready.
- H[arriet] R[andolph] to Margaret and P. J. Randolph, 1831 March 5, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Tallahassee, FL, March 11; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:26)
  Requesting that the family at Edgehill break their two year long silence since her removal to Florida, and describes the advantages of Florida over Virginia. Also relates the elopement of a fifteen year old former pupil of hers, Attaway Willis with Sam Duval.
- Miss H.C. Stearns to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1831 September 6, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; docketed; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:27)
  Written in crosshatch, this letter is difficult to read. Concerning her arrival in Boston, and her interactions with acquaintances there, and the customs and conversation of the "Yankees."
- Miss H.C. Stearns to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1831 December 23, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; docketed; postmarked Boston, MA, January 3; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Concerning her difficulty in opening a school in Boston, her discussing the situation of her competitors there, and congratulates her former pupil, Margaret, on "the prospect a school."
- H[arriet] Randolph to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1832 January 29, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Tallahassee, FL, February 16; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:29)
  Apologizing for her lack of correspondence since her marriage five weeks prior to writing the letter, and concerning her affairs and acquaintances in Florida.
- Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Jane H[ollins] Nicholas Randolph, 1832 February 11, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; postmarked- February 14; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:30)
  Laments his separation from his family due to the [debate in the Virginia Legislature concerning the abolition of slavery]. Randolph claims, "this is a busy time for all those who take an interest in the business going on, subject to be acted on every day. I have been sitting for my portrait at the request of a painter who is taking the portraits of a few of the distinguished orators on the abolition question. He is making a good job of it. He has endeavored to give it the expression of stern & deep feeling which I certainly felt in replying to my opponents & I think has succeeded. My friends tell me that in some of our debates give my adversaries some very fierce looks. I have not given them hard words." He also mentions the payment of several loans that are due, and his desire to return after the legislature ends.
- Mary [?] to Margaret Smith Randolph, ca. [1833-1838] February 6, Describing an outbreak of scarlet fever in Richmond, her own affliction and recovery at Judge Carr's, and its appearance at her school. (Box-folder ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Richmond, VA, February 7; Barrow.)
- [Unidentified] to Miss Margaret [Smith] Randolph, 1833 May 12, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked City of Washington, May 16; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:32)
  Concerning dress making, and explanations of several patterns that she has sent previously. Expressing her thanks for sister Jane's gift of "real Virginia ham." Mentions Nicolas [P. Trist] and Virginia [Jefferson Randolph Trist's] plan to go to Cuba. The author also claims that "I wish the Virginians would get into the way of importing germans to take the place of slaves; they are hardworking, hon[orable] creatures, [that] work for very low wages."
- Mary [?] to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1833 November 4, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with wax seal; postmarked, VA, November 2; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:33)
  Concerning her travels from Norfolk to Old Point, to Key West, and mentions seeing a ship on its way to Liberia, where "the blacks accompanied by six missionaries and their wives came down in the Steam boat with us today. I saw them go on board, and ere this time suppose they are out of sight of their native land- Oh what a situation is theirs- I never saw more dejected countenances than the females had, and could not help feeling a great deal for them. I trust they may be enabled to do much good in that heathen land."
- Mary [?] to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1833 November 22, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, November 30; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:34)
  Concerning a visit to Richmond, and her plans to visit Edgehill when time affords.
- George Wythe Randolph to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1833 December 30, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with wax seal; postmarked Pensacola, FL, December 31. (Box-folder 1:35)
  Concerning his life at sea, and mentions [Frederick Marryat's] Peter Simple. He also states that his "Commodore is an old dotard," but praises his Captain, and speculates on his ship's destination. George says that "it is thought that we are to sail for Jamaica to protect the American property as a revolt of the negroes is constantly expected or perhaps we may sail to Vera Cruz in the Gulf of Mexico" to pick up stranded members of the recently sunk Schooner Porpoise.
- Peggy Nicholas to Mrs. Thomas Jefferson Randolph [Martha Jefferson Randolph], 1834 March 7, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Baltimore, MA, March 6; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:36)
  Registers her uneasiness at their long silence during turbulent times, and states, "I have been trembling for poor [Thomas] Jefferson [Randolph] in these sad times of pressure, and justly fear that half the country will be ruined before Congress decides which is to blame, the President [Andrew Jackson], or the Bank," and continues to relate the conditions of various family members.
- S. E. N[icholas] to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1834 March 31, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:37)
  Concerning making shirts, and bonnets, concerning mourning protocol, and requesting that after her own death that others do not dress in mourning clothes. She also mentions [Thomas Jefferson Randolph's] election, and that she "do[es]n't wish him success," because she claims that a man in debt should not enter a public life.
- Mary [?] to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1834 April 2, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with wax seal; postmarked Tallahassee, FL, April; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:38)
  Concerning her acquaintances in Tallahassee, and asking to be remembered to a variety of family members.
- George Wythe Randolph to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1834 May 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Pensacola, FL, May 7. (Box-folder 1:39)
  Mentions meeting with Mr. [Nicholas P.] Trist, and the broken engagement between Lewis [Randolph] and the sister of Richard Meade. He claims that soon Miss Meade will be worth $80000, "and a man is a fool in [his] humble opinion that wouldn't marry any hag upon earth for that fortune." He also mentions his life as a midshipman.
- S. E. N[icholas] to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1834 July 2, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address. (Box-folder 1:40)
  Chastising her for her extravagant fashion choices, providing her with fashion advice, and asking about what kind of wedding she is to have.
- Miss H. C. Stearns to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1834 November 9, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with wax seal; postmarked Northhampton, MS, November 10; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:41)
  Concerning the illness of Miss Henrietta Smith, and her visits to Cambridge, and Boston. She also inquires about several of Margaret's relations, and whether Margaret has read Spark's American Biography where she has "in it a life of Capt. Smith which throws great luster upon the character of Pocahontas."
- Miss H.C. Stearns to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1835 March 27, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with partial wax seal; postmarked March 30; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:43)
  Concerning Margaret's meeting with Patsy and Mr. Taylor, and laments "the resurrection of the ghost of [Margaret's] dyspepsia." She also mentions her sister's outbreak of mumps, and her solitude in New Hampshire.
- George Wythe Randolph to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1835 July 25, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; postmarked New York, July 27. (Box-folder 1:44)
  Concerning life aboard the U.S. Frigate Constitution, and outbreaks of illness on board. He also relates an anecdote about missing his mother's visit in Boston.
- Septimia Randolph to Margaret S[mith] Randolph, 1836 January 20, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked City of Washington; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:45)
  Concerning fashions, and dancing, including her desire to learn how to waltz, "but not to waltz with a gentleman for [she] do[es] not approve of it."
- Martha Jefferson Randolph to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1836 February 2, ALS, 1 p.; with address on verso; docketed; postmarked Boston, MA, February 3; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:46)
  Concerning very cold weather in Boston, with some comparison to the weather in Virginia.
- E. A. Randolph to Margaret Randolph, 1836 June 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address. (Box-folder 1:47)
  Concerning the death of his mother. Mentions [Meriwether] Lewis [Randolph's] inability to return home, and his inclination to join Lewis in Arkansas the next fall to engage in land speculation, and other family matters.
- Margaret Smith to Margaret Smith Randolph, [1836]? July 26, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Baltimore, MD, July 26. (Box-folder 1:48)
  Concerning the unexpected death of a child of her cousin's, and their family's sadness.
- Margaret Smith to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1836 July 30, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Baltimore, MD, July 31; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:49)
  Concerning a visit for "that stranger from the South," and his engagement to a "horrid bad old hag who has taken him in and persuaded him to marry her in her old days," and inquiring about the conditions of various family members including the rumored engagement of Cary Ann.
- Margaret Smith to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1836 September 16, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Baltimore, MD, September 17; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:50)
  Concerning her safe return to Baltimore, detailing her journey there, and relating the conditions of various people she met along the way.
- Thomas Sully to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1836 October 18, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; with partial wax seal. (Box-folder 1:51)
  Concerning his work as a copier, and suggesting that he also make a frame for the item.
- Cary Anne Randolph to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1837 January-, ALS, 1 p.; with address on verso; docketed; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:52)
  Sending copies of "Cousin Beverly's letter," and says that her mother "begs that [Thomas Jefferson Randolph] will think again before [he] allows [him]self to be nominated for Governor, that she cannot get along possibly without [him]."
- Margaret Smith Randolph to "Papa" [Thomas Jefferson Randolph], 1837 January 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:53)
  Writing on behalf of her mother, rebuking him for not writing them sooner, and claiming that they "[we]re all delighted to hear that [he] w[as] not governor." They are all anxiously awaiting his return.
- Mrs. Jane Harrison Randolph and Thomas Jefferson Randolph II to Thomas Jefferson Randolph I, 1837 February 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; docketed. (Box-folder 1:54)
  Informing him that one of their tobacco houses burned to the ground, and suggesting that it was arson. Jane relates that Mr. Garrison's "suspicions rest on 'big Buck' & [she] believe[s] Edmond. [She] think[s] most of the negroes think it must have been set on fire." She later provides him with Nicholas P. Trist's address in Havana, Cuba.
- Thomas Sully to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1837 February 21, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:55)
  Cleaning instructions written on the same leaf as a "promise to deliver" "one box [of] merchandise."
- George Wythe Randolph to Margaret Smith Randolph, 1837 April 13, ALS, 2 pp. with attached address leaf; postmarked Portsmouth, VA, April 13. (Box-folder 1:56)
  Concerning his difficulty engaging in letter writing, and informing her of his plans to visit Edge Hill that May.
- Mary [?] to Margaret Randolph, 1837 April 14, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Tallahassee, FL, April 17. (Box-folder 1:57)